Good morning, church. Good to see all of you this morning. I want to welcome all of you.
If we haven't met yet, my name is Pete. I'm one of the pastors here, and I get to share
God's Word with us this morning. If you want to open up your Bibles to Ephesians chapter
one, that's where we're going to be looking into today. As Bo was mentioning earlier,
we're kind of just starting this process of going through the book of Ephesians. It's
been an exciting season for our church as we just get kind of kicked off with a new ministry
year. New life groups have started. A lot of new people are coming and checking out
our church. I do want to welcome those of you who are visiting us today. Really glad you're here.
Hope you get to meet God and see some of what he's doing in our church family this morning.
And I hope all of you already have, as we were just discussing with each other,
just a lot of ways that you are being blessed and growing closer to the Lord. I think one thing I
have to share that really encourages me and has been a blessing to me is just seeing people
actually like really pursuing God. I've been so encouraged by that. And whether that's in like
just after our Sunday celebration, seeing people stick around a little longer just to pray
and seek God, even seeing people like praying for each other, ministering to each other,
just here, or even people coming up to receive prayer from our prayer team. And just hearing,
like as I meet up with people, hearing people saying like, yeah, I'm reading this in the scripture
these days, and God's speaking to me this way. It's just been so encouraging to be part of a
spiritual family where it's not just about kind of us living in community together, but us as a
community really seeking God together. So turn to someone next to you real quick and say, it's good
to seek God together? All right. And I think this is just a great way for us to be starting
this year of ministry, and especially as we shared about our annual theme of higher calling
and really wanting to rise above temporary pursuits and live for God's eternal purposes,
just seeing many of us saying, I want a closer relationship with God. And I think as we seek
that closer relationship and fellowship with him, well, other things will come out of that,
Like we've been talking about a life of faith or even a life of ministry.
That comes out of the relationship with God that we're living in.
And so we're going to really be digging deep into that, especially here in Ephesians chapter 1.
And we'll keep going in that throughout the year.
But I'm excited to get into that this morning.
And for us to really dig into and think about what does it look like to not just know the gospel,
but then live in the truth of the gospel together.
And I think that's something that's really powerful that can really change things in
our lives and in the world around us.
And actually to get started, just with kind of a quick illustration of that, I wonder how
many of you here, if you want to, you can raise your hand, you don't have to, but how many
of you are familiar with this historical period called the Troubles in Northern Ireland?
Okay, there's like a couple of you that know what that is.
Okay, it's all right, but some of you, when I describe it, you'll maybe be like, oh, okay,
yeah, I've heard of that before.
There is this period in Northern Ireland known as the Troubles, and this started around the 1960s, and it started with this conflict about what the future of Northern Ireland would be.
And it's something that really kind of took over that whole country for about 30 years, where there was this ongoing conflict, and it was a conflict between two parties, two groups of people.
One of those were the nationalists or the republicans who were mostly Catholic, and
these were people who wanted a united Ireland, who wanted like Ireland and Northern Ireland
to be in unity together.
And the other party were the unionists or the loyalists.
These were mostly Protestant, and these are people who wanted Northern Ireland to remain
part of the United Kingdom.
And so there was this whole conflict over this, and it wasn't just like a political
conflict, like politicians shaking their fingers at each other.
it erupted into urban warfare, where paramilitary groups like the Irish Republican Army or the
Ulster Volunteer Force, you know, there were just consistent attacks, car bombings, shootings,
all these kinds of things happening over that 30-year period with different spikes, and then
like kind of a lull, and then another spike. But it was a consistent period of violence for three
decades. Over 3,600 people were killed during the Troubles, and estimates of between 30,000 and
50,000 additional injuries during that time. So this was not a small thing. This was something
that really took over this whole nation. And in that time, neighborhoods became segregated.
And they were segregated along those party lines, where if people that were part of these different
parties wouldn't live in the same neighborhood with each other, they kind of blocked off these
neighborhoods with what they called peace lines. But actually, what a peace line meant is if you
cross it, there's not going to be any peace. Like, you're going to get attacked. You might get killed
if you go into the wrong neighborhood. So it was an incredibly divisive time in Northern Ireland's
history, and political solutions didn't seem to be going anywhere. Over these decades, politicians
tried to solve these problems. They tried to start negotiations, but anything that they tried
just stalled out, collapsed, because everyone's just so suspicious of each other. Nobody trusts
each other, to be true to their word. And so no solutions really went anywhere. And during these
times, I mentioned that one of these parties was predominantly Protestant and the other
predominantly Catholic. It wasn't necessarily a religious conflict, but it was more of a
political or a social conflict, and yet they kind of broke down into those groups. And so even a lot
of the institutional churches, Protestant and Catholic churches, would kind of buy into that
tribalism of their surrounding society and sort of pick sides and kind of see the others as enemies
and all that kind of stuff was going on as well. But at the same time, there were believers in
Christ in that country who wanted to live differently, who wanted to see a different
solution. So for instance, there was one group called the Cori Mila community that actually
became a space where Protestants and Catholics from warring neighborhoods would get together,
they would live, they would eat, they would pray, they would dialogue together and really find unity
through faith in Christ. And this was something, a community that started to bring some healing
to the nation. Along with that, many clergy people at that time, on both sides, Catholic and Protestant,
would kind of act behind the scenes to open lines of communication and negotiation between these
warring factions. And so they would talk with opposing politicians, they would talk with these
opposing paramilitary groups and try to kind of bring people together as trusted intermediaries
in those conflicts. So the clergy kind of stepped up to try to play those roles. And most powerfully,
most substantially, there were many followers of Jesus at that time who chose to publicly forgive
those who had murdered their family members. Came out and publicly said that. And in doing so,
became a powerful witness of the gospel to bring reconciliation and restoration of those
relationships and in those communities. And the fruit of these believers living out their faith
and demonstrating the gospel in this way led to actually real change in this country. That
culminated specifically in what was called the Good Friday Agreement that was made on April 10th in
1998. This was kind of a huge turning point in this conflict, that after 30 years of violence and
bitterness and division and hatred, that finally these parties came together and said, we're going
to make peace, and we're going to put an end to this violence. And then there were still some
things that happened after that, but that largely brought about the end of this period known as
the Troubles. Now, I share that today partly because I think it's just a great testimony of the power
of the gospel to bring real change in the lives of people and even in communities. But at the same
time, as we think about that, and I want us to know there is that power, we also recognize that
in a fallen world, these kind of political agreements come and go. It doesn't mean that
there's no more issues, that it will never flare up again, or that everything is totally solved.
But today, as we look into our passage in Ephesians 1, we're going to see actually a greater
and more ultimate hope and unity empowered by the gospel message. And we're going to explore
the power of the gospel to deal with the problem of sin in our lives and ultimately unite all
things in Christ. That's what we're going to talk about today. I'm going to go ahead and give you
our one thing as we start out here today. A lot of times I save it at the end, but I'll give it to
you at the beginning. It's to trust God's gracious plan to unite all things in Christ. Trust God's
gracious plan to unite all things in Christ. And we're just taking short passages in Ephesians as
we go through it this year. So today we're going to go through verses 7 through 10. I'll go ahead
and read this for us. It says this, in him we have redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of
our trespasses, according to the riches of his grace, which he lavished upon us in all wisdom
and insight, making known to us the mystery of his will, according to his purpose, which he set
forth in Christ as a plan for the fullness of time, to unite all things in Christ, things in
heaven and things on earth in him. Amen. Let me pray for us as we've read God's word. Lord, we invite
you once again into this time, into this spiritual family that you have brought together and formed
for your purposes. We invite you here, Lord, because we want to hear from you. We want you to speak to
us through your holy word, Lord, to give us hope, to give us direction, to show us the power of the
gospel message, to lead us in living in that gospel truth and power, to be a testimony of your
saving grace, Lord, and to live in the joy of that truth together. God, we pray that you come and do
this work in each and every one of us today, God, and in us as a community together. Lead us in your
word and in the life you've called us to, Lord. Lead us into that higher calling that you have
for each one of us. In Jesus' name we pray. Amen. Amen. So as we look into today's passage, many of
you probably remember, if you were with us last week, we looked at verses 3 through 6 in Ephesians
1, and we heard how the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ has blessed us in Christ with
every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places. And we started to unpack a little bit what those
spiritual blessings were. But we know it's going to go on through the rest of Ephesians 1. We saw
some of those spiritual blessings, like being chosen as holy and blameless children of God that
were adopted as God's daughters and sons, as children of the King. And today, we're going to
see more of those blessings unfold and be invited to live in those together and kind of see the
ultimate purpose behind those blessings as well. So as we start to dig into this passage, what we
first want to focus in on are some really powerful words like redemption, forgiveness, and grace.
And these are like pretty common Christian terms. If you hang out with Christians or in the church
long enough, you'll probably hear these words a lot of different ways. People kind of use them
very frequently among Christians. For some of you who may be new to the church, and I want to
welcome you if you are new to the church, if you're new, checking out the Christian faith, exploring,
asking questions. Maybe a friend invited you. We're so glad you're here. We want to make sure
everyone's on the same page of what these mean. But also, even for those of us who are Christians,
we may sometimes throw these terms around without really digging in and knowing what it is that
we're saying when we use these terms. And so we want to, all of us, get on the same page with
that here today. And so let's think about redemption and forgiveness to start. I'll give you just
Greek background of these words real quick. The word translated as redemption, that's
apolitrosis. It means to release or set free with the implied analogy to the process of freeing a
slave. So to set free, to liberate, to deliver, to redeem. So this is specifically talking about
buying someone out of slavery. That's what redemption means. That's what it means to
redeem. We're not talking about a general idea. We're not talking about maybe like a football team
trying to redeem themselves or something. We're talking about redeeming out of slavery. That's
what this means. Then if we look at forgiveness, what's that? Where's that come from? It's a Greek
word, aphesis. It means to remove the guilt resulting from wrongdoing. So if somebody is
guilty because of something they've done wrong, aphesis, forgiveness, that means to remove
that guilt somehow. So when we look into this passage and we're trying to understand what it
is talking about, it's talking about that this is what Jesus has done for us. This is what happens
when we are in Christ, and as we look at this here, we're not only seeing what Jesus has done
for us, we also get to see the other side of the coin of what sin actually does in our lives,
and so I want us to dig in there a little bit. As much as it's not fun to talk about sin,
it's important because if we don't talk about the reality of sin, we're not going to really
understand and appreciate what it is that Jesus has done for us, so specifically, if we just take
the flip side of this coin, we can understand in this passage that what sin does is it makes us
guilty and enslaved. That's what sin does. And let's dig into that a little bit. Like when I say
sin makes us guilty and enslaved, I'm referring to the spiritual effect of sin on our lives.
I also don't want us to forget that we're not merely victims of sin, but we're perpetrators
of sin. Sin is not just something we're victims of and we're just kind of passively like, oh,
sin happens to me. No, we sin. We do things that are against God's will. We rebel against his
revealed word, his command. We do things that offend his honor and glory. We do things that
sin against one another as well. We all do that. The effect of that on our lives is that we become
guilty and enslaved. And so think about this here. Paul, as he's writing this letter to the church in
Ephesus, he's not coming up with these as like new ideas out of nowhere. He, in all of this, he's
referring back to the Old Testament that the Jewish people had known for centuries at this
point. And he's thinking probably about things like Proverbs 5.22. It says,
the iniquities of the wicked ensnare him, and he is held fast in the cords of sin.
So he's saying when we fall into sin, we actually become ensnared by it, trapped by it,
unable to get out of it. If I could describe what that might actually look like just in a
very simple example. Like, just imagine that a person has been dishonest about a seemingly small
matter. Maybe they told what they thought was a little white lie to get out of the consequences
of something, okay? So, maybe like, oh, did you, you know, maybe something like, did you leave the
toilet seat up? No, I didn't do that. Somebody else must have come along and done that. Okay,
well, it seems like a little white lie to get out of being in trouble for not putting the toilet
the seat down. It seems small. But now imagine, somebody else comes along and says, well, no one
else has gone in and out of that bathroom. Maybe now that person's kind of stuck. Now, okay, I need
to come up with another lie to cover up my previous lie if I don't want to take responsibility for it.
And so I come up with something of like, oh, maybe the dog went in there and did it.
And then someone says, oh, but the dog's been outside for the last two hours. Oh,
God. Maybe the cat. I don't know. You see, people start coming up with lies to maintain lies. And
the further you go down that path, now significant relationships are on the line. And a person's
reputation in front of others are on the line. And this becomes a snare wrapped around a person
that started with just a small seed of seemingly meaningless dishonesty that now has ensnared that
person, where now they have to keep that lie going and try to use deception to avoid responsibility
and save face, and that becomes habitual. It becomes the way we live. And you can apply that
to anything, right? I'm just using a very small, simple example. How much more powerful is that
snare, that enslavement, when it deals with things that are of heavier weight and their impact on our
lives and on those around us. And I want us to realize here as we think about this, that this
starts affecting us in a lot of different ways. And this ends up damaging the relationship with
people around us, but especially damaging our relationship with God. That's the biggest deal
here. We tend to think and be more aware of how sin affects relationship with people, when somebody's
offended, when trust is broken, things like that. But this most deeply affects our relationship with
God. And here again, Paul, he's not coming up with these days out of nowhere. He's probably
thinking way back to the beginning in a creation account. Go back to Genesis chapter 2 when what
does God tell Adam? It says, the Lord God commanded the man saying, you may surely eat of
every tree of the garden, but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil you shall not eat,
For in the day that you eat of it, you shall surely die.
From the beginning, God said, hey, if you do this thing I'm telling you not to do,
it's not a small matter.
It's going to lead to death.
And here, really think about that.
How easily we fall into this and the destruction that brings in our relationship with God.
And let me show you this painting real quick.
This is my favorite painting of the Garden of Eden.
And I've probably shared it with our church before.
It's by Thomas Cole.
And I love this painting because in most depictions of the Garden of Eden, what do you see?
In most depictions of the Garden of Eden, you see like the tree is right there with the fruit on it.
And Adam and Eve, they're just hanging out there in all their glory, right?
And then there's the serpent.
Maybe the serpent is wrapped around the tree or like they're kind of on the branch of the tree whispering in Eve's ear or something.
And it's almost like, oh, this temptation is just like looming over you.
And it's like the only thing you can see.
But I think this is much more accurate.
Where are Adam and Eve in this?
You can't even see him probably from where you are there on the like bottom center left.
I don't know if you can maybe see him there.
And it paints the picture much more realistically.
This glorious, beautiful, abundant, fruitful creation that God made for humanity
and placed them in it where they would have everything they need to live
and all of those created things to enjoy, everything that they need.
And God says, hey, just one thing.
Just one thing.
Don't eat the tree.
Don't eat the fruit from the tree way over there.
and yet this is what humanity falls into and God says that is going to bring death
it's important for us to wrestle with these things because we live in a culture that
makes light of sin as if it kind of doesn't really matter and so some of us forget the
enormous problem that sin is for us it enslaves us it covers us in guilt and shame it leads to our
spiritual death. We'll talk about more of that in Ephesians chapter 2. Especially it separates us
from God. And we need to recognize that, like how serious an issue that is, and that we can't
rescue ourselves from this. We can't fix this problem ourselves. And as we live dealing with
this problem of sin, and even in relationship with other people, we have a strong tendency to
magnify the severity of other people's sins and point our fingers at others, while we tend to
kind of minimize the severity of our own sins and think they're not such a big deal.
But if even eating a piece of fruit off a tree is something that offends God to the point of
death, maybe we should wrestle with this. Like J.I. Packer writes, there can be no small sins
against a great God. And so we can't minimize this. As much as we don't like talking about it,
I don't like talking about sin. As much as we don't like talking about it, we have to wrestle
with this, to even understand what it is that Christ has done for us. And again, this is why it's
such good news that what we find out in this passage, the first side of the coin that we skipped
over for a second, is that Jesus forgives and redeems us. Jesus forgives and redeems us. And
again, Paul's not coming up with new ideas here. Paul sees in Christ the fulfillment of everything
that has gone beforehand, everything in the Old Testament that he knows. He's pointing out to us
here, number one, it is specifically through the blood of Jesus that is shed on the cross that
secures our forgiveness and our redemption and our adoption, all of those things. But these are
all pointing back toward things that were first set up in the Old Testament. So for instance,
if we go back to the Old Testament book of Leviticus, that lays out the sacrificial system
that was used to atone for sin during that period of history. To give you like a quick touch point
to help us understand what we're talking about here, like why through the blood of Jesus? Why
does the blood of Jesus matter? That seems like a very strange thing to our ears, right? But
understand this the way that it's shown to us in Leviticus. Leviticus 17, 11 says,
for the life of the flesh is in the blood, and I have given it for you on the altar to make
atonement for your souls, for it is the blood that makes atonement by the life. So you look at that,
And then you scan through some other chapters, like chapters 1 through 7 and 16 of Leviticus,
and you start to realize that in the Bible, blood signifies life surrendered in death.
And blood on the altar represents a life-for-life substitution.
That's what's being presented to us here, that Paul is looking at this through that lens.
And so when we see the blood of Jesus poured out on the cross, now this is a fulfillment of that.
And yet it's not only in the sacrificial system, but even when we look back to the stories of the
Old Testament, like the Passover, many of you are familiar with this, when God rescued the Hebrew
people out of slavery in Egypt, that God brought judgment on the land of Egypt for holding the
Hebrews in slavery, right? And it was through the blood of a lamb that protected the Israelites
from sharing in the judgment on the Egyptian people. So you're probably familiar with this,
But Exodus 12, 21 to 23 says,
the door, and will not allow the destroyer to enter your house to strike you. So when we see
these reference points, we start to understand that for the Israelites, the blood of the sacrifice
on the altar atoned for their sins, and the blood of the Passover land redeemed them out of slavery
and judgment. And so now when we fast forward here, we realize what it is that Christ came to do,
because what happened in the Old Testament, and you know, these things like sacrifices on the
altar or the Passover. These were things the Jewish people did year after year after year
on the day of Yom Kippur, the day of atonement or at the Passover festival. They would do these
things over and over again saying, God, we need you to atone for our sins. God, we need you to
set us free from slavery and judgment. They would do this over and over again. But what Christ
came to do was to do that one time to solve the problem of sin permanently. And the author of
Hebrews describes to us how this happens.
Hebrews 9, 11 to 15.
But when Christ appeared as a high priest of the good things that have come,
then through the greater and more perfect tent,
that's referring to the tabernacle,
not made with hands, that is not of this creation,
he entered once for all into the holy places,
not by the means of the blood of goats and calves,
but by means of his own blood,
thus securing an eternal redemption.
For if the blood of goats and bulls
and the sprinkling of defiled persons with the ashes of a heifer
sanctify for the purification of the flesh
how much more will the blood of Christ
who through the eternal spirit
offered himself without blemish to God
purify our conscience from dead works
to serve the living God
therefore he is the mediator of a new covenant
so that those who are called
may receive the promised eternal inheritance
since a death has occurred that redeems them
from the transgressions committed
under the first covenant
so this is what Jesus came to fulfill
and to do. And the author of Hebrews goes on into chapter 10 and he says,
for since the law has but a shadow of the good things to come, instead of the true form of
these realities, it can never, by the same sacrifices that are continually offered every
year, make perfect those who draw near. What we take from this, brothers and sisters,
is that Jesus offered one perfect sacrifice for sin that secured eternal forgiveness and
redemption, that now that slate is wiped clean, and we can know God. And he didn't just do this
in like a small measure. We find out in this passage he did this according to the riches of
God's grace, according to the riches of God's grace. And we need to understand this about God's
grace. Many people say that God's grace is unmerited favor, unmerited favor from God,
something, receiving something that we didn't earn, and that's true, but that's actually only
like half of it. Because what the reality is, is it's not just that we didn't deserve the good
things that God gave us, it's that we actually also deserved the bad side of guilt and judgment
and slavery to sin that we were living under. Harry Ironside says this, grace is the very opposite
of merit. Grace is not only undeserved favor, but it is favor shown to the one who has deserved the
very opposite. So while we in our sin had rebelled against God, actually deserved judgment for the
sins that we had committed, instead we are given grace. Grace, love, forgiveness, redemption,
restoration, and coming back to God. This is what God's grace secured, and this grace was very
expensive. It came at the price of God's son, Jesus. And it says in verse 8 that he lavished us
with this grace. He lavished it upon us. It wasn't just like a little bit, it was a lot. Like think
about it this way, because in talking here about like according to the riches of God's grace,
we need to understand the difference between somebody giving out of their riches and someone
giving according to their riches. Like maybe I'll put it this way to maybe help us understand a
little bit. Let's just imagine, and some of us, maybe this isn't so hard to imagine, imagine that
you're a college student who is struggling financially, and you're getting close to
graduation, and you've accumulated massive student debt. Let's say it's like $400,000
of high-interest student debt, and I know that's not impossible for some of us here,
okay? And maybe for that $400,000 in student debt, maybe you got a degree that's not going to pay
off very well. Let's just imagine that that might be your reality. And in that reality, let's say
you go out and you're sitting on the Diag one day, just enjoying the rays of sunshine, nice fall
weather, but sitting there wondering, what is my future going to hold with all this debt? And I'm
not sure what job I'm going to get, and things just don't look very good. And so you're sitting
there on the Diag. And as you're sitting there, you just happen to see one of the founders of
Google walking through campus. Larry Page walks by, because he's actually a U of M alumni.
And so he's walking through campus, reliving his undergrad years. He's walking through the Diag,
you know, and he's, I'm going to step on that M. You know, he's just going through,
doing his thing, right? And as he's walking through, you just remember, oh, Larry Page is a
multi-billionaire. Maybe this guy can help me out a little bit. So you flag down Larry Page. Hey,
Larry? Hey, buddy. You get his attention. You explain your situation. I'm in all this debt.
I don't know where I'm going to get a job. I'm going to spend my lifetime paying this off. I
don't know what I'm going to do. And let's say Larry hears you, and he looks, and he says,
he says, man, that sounds really tough. Let's say he grabs his wallet, pulls it out,
pulls out a crisp hundred dollar bill. He says, here you go, buddy. Here you go, friend.
I hope that helps out a little bit.
Larry, in this situation, has just given out of his riches.
Doesn't make much of a difference for him or for you, right?
He gave out of his riches.
He didn't give according to his riches.
Let's say instead, same situation, Larry says, hey, let me sit down with you for a second.
Tell me what's going on.
Tell me about yourself and what you're going through.
He hears you out.
He says, hey, I want to help you get started on the right foot.
I don't want you to go through life under this pile of debt.
I'm going to pay off that $400,000 debt.
I'm going to pay it off completely tomorrow.
It's as good as done.
As soon as business opens tomorrow, your debt is paid off.
And not only that, it seems like you might need a place to live.
So why don't you come and move out to Silicon Valley?
I have a luxury apartment out there, and you can live there as long as you want.
Just consider it yours for as long as you need.
And it sounds like you might have a tough time getting a job with that degree.
But you know what?
I can do something about that.
Let me make a call.
I'm going to set up a new job for you and give you a really high salary, great benefits, stock
options at Google. You're going to be all set. And I think you said you don't have a car. Why don't
you just borrow my helicopter whenever you need it, like just to get around, you know, go grocery
shopping or whatever. Just go ahead and take the copter. And he just lays all this out for you,
right? Now here, now Larry has not given out of his riches. He has given according to his riches.
right, according to it. Now, he still has more than enough for that. That probably doesn't make
a dent in his riches anyway either, does it? He could do all of that. But he has given in a way
that is according to the resources that he has available. I share this with you because we need
to understand when it says that God gives to us according to the riches of his grace. He forgives
us and redeems us, and he doesn't just reach into his pocket and kind of throw some spare change
our way. He gives us according to the riches of his grace, which again means at the price of his own
son and means we're given this eternal inheritance that we are now forgiven and redeemed and
restored according to the riches of his grace. Our record of sin is erased. We're welcomed into
the family of God. We're adopted daughters and sons of the king. So when we think about that and
realize, wait a second, if I understand that analogy correctly, that's how deep my debt of sin
was. That's how deep my guilt was. I could have tried a lifetime and never been able to get out
of it. And I couldn't have gotten the positive side either. I couldn't have earned that on my own.
wait, that's the riches of God's grace toward me.
When we start to realize that,
it's a humbling and joyful realization.
And then as we keep going in this passage,
we come to recognize that what God has done for us in Christ
isn't only about us ultimately.
He does love us as his sons and daughters.
He wants to make us his own.
He wants to cancel the record of our debt in sin.
He wants to redeem us out of slavery.
He wants to do all of that, but it's not only about you and me.
He has a greater plan for it that he's been working out since we learned last week.
He's been working out since before the beginning of time, and that plan is to unite all things
in Christ, to unite all things in Christ.
And partly here, I mean, these things are unfolding for us, but I want to take a moment to point
it says here that this is making known to us the mystery. It's making known to us the mystery. And
partly this mystery is actually being laid out and unfolded before us here. And there are even
more places in Ephesians where we see more of the mystery laid out. But I want to pause on this idea
of mystery here for a second. Because I think for many of us, we really struggle that there are
things about our faith in Christ that we do not understand. And I want to ask us to really wrestle
with God about that and come to a place where you can actually accept some mystery in your
relationship with God and your faith in him. Let me put it this way. I've had a good number of
conversations with Muslims over the years, both here in the U.S. as well as overseas in Jordan.
And one of the things I hear most often a question, and a question that many Muslims,
if they're genuinely wanting to know Jesus and understand what Christians believe, many of them
will genuinely ask this question. They'll say, hey, you say you believe in one God, but it looks
like you have three gods, Father, Son, and Spirit. Like, what's up with that? What's with the three
gods when you say you believe in one God thing? Like, I don't understand that. Now, some Muslims
will ask that question more antagonistically, wanting to pick a fight. Some will ask it more
just wanting to understand. And my response to that question is usually along these lines that
I'll say something like, well, you know, as Christians, we believe in one God who exists
eternally in three persons, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. We believe this because that's what's
revealed to us in the pages of Scripture, that you see Father, Son, and Spirit all having the
character and the acts of God, all being identified as God, worshipped, acknowledged as God, and yet
being revealed as one God. So we believe in one God eternally existing in three persons. And I'll
be honest with you, there are some things about how that works, what that means, that are kind
of mysterious to me. I don't fully understand it myself, but I believe it because that's what's
revealed to me in the Word of God. What do you think about that? And they usually say, well,
that still doesn't make much sense to me. How can three exist in one? That just doesn't make any
sense. And rather than trying to give them some analogy like a three-leaf clover or something like
that, I usually respond and say, well, you know what? Isn't God so much greater than us? And
Muslims have a high view of God. We should too. Isn't God so much greater than us? Isn't he so far
beyond our comprehension in his glory, in his righteousness, his holiness, his majesty? Like,
isn't he so much greater than we are? Well, shouldn't there be some things about a God that
great that we can't fully understand? If we could fully understand him, if we could explain
every single thing about him, if we understood everything about who he is, about what he does,
about why he does it, about all of that, wouldn't that mean that that God is actually less than we
are? If we can fit him in our little brains, and if they're honest, usually the people I'm talking
to will say, hmm, I see what you're saying. I see what you're saying. I share that because I think
many of us, we need to wrestle with God, who he is, and his plans in the same kind of way.
I know that's even coming up for some of us right now
as we go through Ephesians.
Maybe we're a little bit confused
about what we talked about today.
How does Jesus' blood forgive our sins?
I'm still not really sure.
Why does that work that way?
I'm not sure if that makes sense to me.
Maybe some of us, that's a little bit mysterious.
As we look at today's passage,
we realize prior generations didn't understand God's plan.
They didn't understand how the Passover
and the sacrifices and the Old Testament laws,
they didn't understand how that worked
and how that pointed to Jesus.
Now we do.
We understand that mystery in a way that they didn't.
For others of us, maybe as we brought up last week,
maybe there's some mystery in how God's sovereignty
and human responsibility and freedom interact.
I'm not sure how this makes sense.
Not sure what to do with that.
There's some mystery there.
We're going to talk about in chapter 2,
the mystery of how God reconciles both Jew and Gentile in Christ.
There's more mystery to be unveiled here.
I share all of this because we need to recognize
that we are less than God.
And like, I mean, 1 Corinthians 13, 12, another letter written by Paul, for now we see in a mirror
dimly, but then face to face. Now I know in part, then I shall know fully, even as I have been fully
known. We're not going to understand everything right now. I thank God that Christian faith,
the scriptures, they're intellectually consistent, reliable, trustworthy. I think they make more
sense out of the world as a worldview by far than any other system philosophically or otherwise that
there is out there. That's all real, and yet there are still some things that we're not fully going
to understand. I share this again to say there should be some room in your faith in Christ for
some mystery, because if there are some things we're not going to fully understand, and I would
ask us to caution ourselves in a couple ways around that, because there's a risk that for some
of us, we want God to be fully within our understanding. So we start actually judging
and critiquing God when we don't understand things about his will. And no matter how we
try to wrestle with God, we should not put ourselves in a place of being judged over
him, critiquing him, saying, God, why don't you just see things the way that I do? I'm
trying to make sense of this for you, God. I'm doing you a favor. For some of us, maybe
it's we try to rescue God from ways we think that his plan doesn't make sense. We think
our way is going to be a better way. I would encourage us to have a humble posture, even as
we study the scriptures, to say God is revealing himself and his plan and his will, these mysteries
to me, and some of it I can understand the way that people in the past couldn't, like the Jewish
people in the Old Testament, they couldn't understand this fully. I can understand this now
because it's revealed to me. There's other stuff I can't fully understand yet, but one day I'm not
going to see through a mirror dimly anymore. I'm going to fully know. And so I can wrestle with
this, but I can also trust and rest in this. And I think this is so important because ultimately
God wants us to be able to rest and trust in him and his word and what's been revealed to us.
So he's making known to us this mystery. And here in this passage, the specific mystery
that's being made known is that God's will, purpose, and plan. He's saying that it's being
laid out for you now. God's telling you directly, this is what it is. My plan, he says, is being set
forth in Christ. That means that his plan is revealed in the person and work of Jesus. It's
fulfilled in Jesus. This is what's being laid out for you here so you can fully understand it. And
this is a plan for the fullness of time. What does that mean? That means that before time began,
it started. That means when time reaches its fulfillment at the end of history, it will be
finished, that means in the fullness of time, because God sees all of it, he is going to bring
to fulfillment his plans and his purposes. And specifically that plan and purpose is to unite
all things in heaven and earth. To unite all things in heaven and earth. And that means that
his plan is to completely redeem and restore the division between sinful humanity in a broken
creation and God's eternal kingdom of righteousness and peace. That's what God wants to do.
And remember, like, does this have to do with conflict between people?
Like, warring societies, armies fighting each other, politicians screaming at each other,
cultures hating each other.
Like, does it have to do with that?
Yes, it does.
But where that redemption and reconciliation happens is not just among those people by themselves on earth.
It only happens in relationship with God through Jesus Christ.
That's the only way that it happens.
And we see that being described for us in Revelation, don't we?
Revelation 21, 1-5, one of my favorite passages.
Then I saw a new heaven and a new earth.
For the first heaven and the first earth had passed away, and the sea was no more.
And I saw the holy city, New Jerusalem, coming down out of heaven from God,
prepared as a bride adorned for her husband.
And I heard a loud voice from the throne saying,
Behold, the dwelling place of God is with man.
He will dwell with them, and they will be his people.
And God himself will be with them as their God.
He will wipe away every tear from their eyes, and death shall be no more.
Neither shall there be mourning, nor crying, nor pain anymore, for the former things have passed away.
And he who was seated on the throne said, Behold, I am making all things new.
This is the hope that we look forward to.
God is going to, in his great plan, his will, his purpose,
he is going to unite all things in heaven and earth, bringing everything together
at the throne of Jesus Christ with everything being made new,
all the stain of sin being wiped away, nobody enslaved to sin any longer.
That is God's plan and purpose that he desires for all of us.
And I think every single one of us here right now can recognize
this is definitely not the way the world is right now.
And in fact, we should be honest that the world around us,
trying to fix itself, where there's a lot of good things people can try to do,
People can try to do great humanitarian work,
great acts of generosity and servant,
humanly speaking, great things.
It's great that people are doing that.
But the world is not going to fix itself apart from Christ.
We should be honest with that
and say we actually have a greater hope,
a greater solution,
a mystery offered to us in the pages of Scripture
through God's Son, Jesus Christ.
And really, when we look at the world around us
and see that lack of hope,
we should also be able to look at ourselves
as Christians, as the church,
and realize that maybe we're not living this out right now either.
We aren't yet that bride adorned for her husband.
Why is that?
Because we're not really living in the truth of the gospel
that we're talking about today.
So think about that.
This is a great challenge for us.
This idea of higher calling that we have this year.
Again, there's parts of that higher calling that are about serving God, taking steps of faith,
stuff like that that I think are beautiful and wonderful to see, but it must start in our
relationship with God. Are we living in relationship with God and then even with
other people in a way that reflects and magnifies and testifies to God's plan accomplished through
his son, Jesus Christ? And I think the hard reality of that is for many of us, this is not what our
lives look like right now. God is inviting us into that. And for many of us, I want us to wrestle
with the fact that this might actually be damaging to our faith, the way we're living right now.
Because while God says you're forgiven and redeemed, you're purchased out of slavery,
the record of your guilt is wiped clean. For many of us, that's not how we're living in
relationship with God or with other people. How do I know that? How many of us are living right
now ensnared in that web of lies and deception. It's got a hold on us. We're scared. If we bring
it to the surface, we bring it to God. If we bring it to other people, I feel like we're going to be
rejected. How many of us, living condemned by past mistakes, were scared to death that somebody
would find out what we've done before? And when we live that way, while we say we believe the gospel
of Jesus Christ, everything in our lives, our relationship with God, our relationship with
others actually testifies the opposite. And this is why today I don't want to gloss over this.
I don't want to gloss over this problem of sin and how this affects us. I want us to really dig
into that and realize God has revealed his plan through Jesus so that we can join him in that plan.
Like that one thing I shared at the beginning, trust God's gracious plan to unite all things in
Christ, but I want us to really wrestle with this. What does this mean for me? What does this mean
for us? How do I not just say I believe in these truths like we recited the Apostles' Creed earlier,
but how do I actually live in this? Myself, with God, and even in relationship with my brothers and
sisters in Christ. So can I give us some things here to reflect and pray about as we close out
our time here this morning? First question I want to ask us to think through is, how do you deal
with the problem of sin in your life?
How do you respond to that?
Because all of us have sin.
1 John says,
if anyone claims they don't have sin,
he's a liar and the truth is not in him.
All of us have sin.
There's not a single one of us who doesn't.
How do we deal with that?
I think what the world does
around us who doesn't know Christ
is hide from sin.
Pretend it doesn't exist.
Try to justify that sin.
Oh, well, here's,
I have this justification
for why what I did
is actually the right thing to do,
even though I know that it's wrong.
Sometimes it's in comparing ourselves with others.
Oh, well, yeah, I did this, but man, that person over there,
they're much worse than me.
They did that, so what I did isn't really that bad.
Or even trying to redeem ourselves.
Yeah, maybe I did that bad thing,
but look at all the good things I'm doing.
Look at how kind I am to others.
Look at the ways I serve.
Look at how generous I am.
Maybe even, as we realize, probably realize for a second,
this isn't just how the world deals with sin.
This is how many of us deal with sin.
Maybe it's even, look how much I'm serving God.
God, look how faithful I am in worshiping you.
God, look how much more scripture I know
than that person next to me.
God, look how many more missions trips I've gone on.
God, look how much I sacrifice my time and energy for you.
God, doesn't that cover over these things that I've done?
And brothers and sisters,
it's not just that this is like the wrong way to handle it.
You don't have to live under this weight any longer.
You don't have to hide.
You don't have to pretend.
You don't have to justify yourself.
You don't have to compare and compete with others.
You don't have to try to redeem yourself any longer.
As the church, as followers of Jesus,
we can actually be honest about our sin
and live in freedom and our need for grace
because the debt's already been paid by Jesus Christ.
It's already been paid.
You don't have to pay for it anymore.
You don't have to hide from it.
You don't have to cover it up anymore.
You don't have to try to redeem yourself anymore.
The price has already been paid.
Can you tell somebody next to you,
And I want to encourage us.
Like, learn, like, how do you deal with this problem of sin?
The way that we do that, the way we do that is actually first with God and then with others.
That we bring that to God and say, God, this is the way that I've turned away from you.
I'm not going to hide from it anymore.
I'm not going to pretend that it was okay anymore.
I'm not going to justify myself anymore.
I'm not going to compare anymore.
God, I'm just going to be honest about my sin.
and I'm gonna bring it to you
and I'm gonna trust that Jesus
through that blood shed on the cross,
that blood that redeems,
that blood that forgives,
that it set me free.
The weight can be lifted from my shoulders.
I don't need to hide from you anymore, God,
and I don't need to hide from others either
and then even in relationship with others.
We can bring those things into the light.
We can bring it to one another and say,
this is how I've sinned.
Can I tell you,
this is one of the most important things
that I've had to learn. If I could just share personally, very briefly, I remember I had to
learn this lesson the hard way because I, like everybody else, grew up, this is the way you do
it. You hide, you justify, you pretend, you try to avoid it. But I remember probably roughly 20
years ago or so, I was here in our church. I've been following Jesus for a few years, thought I
knew the right answers. But I was here, I was serving, I was serving as a leader in our church.
By the way, having a leadership title doesn't mean you're not sinning, just FYI.
and I was serving in leadership and there was another person serving in leadership and I didn't
like some of the way that he decisions he was making ways he was leading stuff like that and
I was not in a good place spiritually I don't think again like being a leader doesn't mean you're not
struggling spiritually and out of that there was just this bitterness in my heart this judgment in
my heart and I started I was just like getting really angry at this other person serving in
leadership. And I was, I would, and I knew I shouldn't, like, do anything really outwardly,
but what I would do is, like, I would, you know, kind of say passive-aggressive comments
to him and, like, to him or about him in meetings that we were having. I would, like, go and, like,
tell somebody else, like, man, you see what that decision that guy made? Like, it's a stupid
decision. Like, I would, and I would do everything but directly confront the issue. And in doing
that, eventually, somebody came to me and said, Pete, what are you doing? What's wrong? And I had
to realize this sin in my heart that I somehow thought I was better than. I somehow thought
that this other person was so much worse than me. And instead of dealing with that in a way,
like, lavished with the grace of God like we can do, instead, I was doing that passive aggressively,
critically, condemning him, tearing him down. I was doing all that stuff. And it wasn't until a
brother came along and confronted me and said, Pete, what you're doing is not right. This is not
how you live in the grace and mercy of God. And he challenged me, and I realized I had to go to that
brother. I had to confess to him. I had to say, hey, I apologize. I've been critical and judgmental
toward you. Will you forgive me? And you know what? That brother forgave me. We were able to love each
other, care for each other, be friends with each other, because the grace of God covered that. I had
to learn that the hard way. My fear is that we can come here, we can do the things we do on Sunday
in our life groups, all that, we can serve, we can do all the stuff that we do, and behind the scenes
where we're actually living our relationship with God and others is just rotten with sin.
So how do you deal with that? And by the way, I just want to give an invitation here today. There
are some of you, maybe you are checking out the Christian faith, maybe you know the weight of trying
to deal with your own sin and maybe you've known it for a long time. You've been trying to hide.
You've been trying to pay the price yourself and trying to pretend it isn't enslaving you
when you really know that it is. Can I invite you today to be in Christ with us? It's not that
this is a perfect community, but we follow a Savior who has given his life for us. He shed
his blood on the cross, not just for the person sitting next to you, but for you. And today I want
you to be in Christ, meaning that you trust his sacrifice for you, that through the blood he shed
on the cross, he has set you free from slavery, and he's set you free from guilt. It's atoned for.
Can you pray to him today? Trust in him today. Say, I'm placing my faith in Jesus as my Savior today.
I want to follow him and live in his grace today. I would love for you to do that even on your own
now in your relationship with God, but maybe come and talk to one of the prayer team afterward
and say, hey, I'm choosing to place my faith in Jesus today.
I want to give you that invitation this morning.
As we want to live in that together,
can I also ask you, are you living in unity
with your brothers and sisters in Christ?
Are you living in unity?
Where have things like unforgiveness,
comparison, gossip, jealousy,
simple personality differences,
where have these caused division among us?
And is there maybe a conflict or a conversation
you've been avoiding rather than trusting God
to redeem and restore?
And lastly, thirdly, do you trust God
to work out his purpose and plan?
This is kind of getting back to the mystery stuff
I shared earlier.
A lot of us, we struggle to really follow and trust God
because we're like, God, it doesn't make sense to me.
I don't see the whole road map yet.
Again, I talked before, God doesn't give you a road map,
God gives you a compass.
We're like, God, I just can't follow you yet.
I can't fully trust because I don't know everything.
Can I ask you today, can you trust that God has a purpose?
God has a plan.
It's a plan bigger than you or I could possibly conceive of
because it's been from before time until the end of time.
But his plan will be accomplished through his son, Jesus Christ.
Can we believe that today?
Because when we trust that plan, then we can actually rest
and have peace in our hearts even when we don't fully understand.
end. And if we trust in that plan, then we can actually take steps of faith in response to God.
And even when we can't fully control everything, but we can respond to God and say, God, I'm going
to take a step of faith today. And a lot of times we think, oh, it's a step of faith. Yeah, that's
serving God in some way. That's going on missions. Maybe that step of faith today is simply confessing
your sin to God. Saying, God, I can't fix this. Maybe that step of faith today is I need to reach
out to my sister because I need to confess something to her. Maybe that step of faith is
I need to place my faith in Jesus for the first time, even though I can't fully understand.
Can we trust that God's plans are better than ours and then live in that truth together? Let's
spend some time in response today. Can I invite us to stand together? As we're standing here,
again, I want to just kind of create some space here for us personally to respond to God first.
So just kind of bow your head with me
and maybe you want to just reflect through
some of those questions I just asked you.
How am I dealing with the problem of sin?
Am I living in unity?
God wants to unite everything in heaven and earth.
All those warring nations,
all those tribes that hate one another,
all those divided relationships,
everything he wants to bring together in Christ.
Am I simply living in unity with my brothers and sisters?
Am I trusting that God's plans are better than mine?
Maybe you want to just sit with those questions here
for a moment before God.
And as we have this time to respond,
just as I've shared before,
we really want this to be like
we must seek intimacy with God.
We must seek fellowship with him.
Have the hard conversation.
Rest in the truth.
Rejoice in the promises fulfilled in Christ.
Celebrate his faithfulness.
Mourn the things that have been lost.
Be honest about the pain.
Be honest about the confusion.
Bring that to God and in relationship with him in this space,
let's believe that he is calling us to that higher calling
that starts with deep relationship and fellowship with him.
I'm going to just pray for that for us here for a moment.
After I pray, just kind of have a short open time
just for you to pray and seek the Lord
and then the worship team is going to lead us in a couple songs.
And let's let this be a space to respond to God,
to seek him, to say, God, I need to know you.
I must know you more.
So God, we invite you here again.
Come, Holy Spirit, work in each and every heart.
Give us the gift of faith and trust.
Set us free in this moment.
The power of the blood of Jesus Christ.
Sanctify us through and through.
Set us free from the things that have been enslaving us
and bonding us.
Wash us clean, God, of all the guilt and all the shame.
Invite us into your great plan
to know that our lives have a purpose
to be part of what you're doing until the end of time.
Invite us into that, Lord, and especially draw us near, Lord,
that we would be close to you,
that we would know you more,
that we would know you so personally and intimately in this moment, Lord.
Come and speak and move.
Have your way in us in this space.
In Jesus' name.